Henrique Sposito

COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENTIST

Profile

My research leverages advanced text analysis techniques, such as supervised machine learning, to investigate how authenticity, problem construction, and urgency appear and change over time and across settings in political discourses. I also develop, contribute, and help maintain several R packages that assist researchers dealing with multiple, overlapping, and uncertain datasets across various domains of global governance.

Education

PhD in International Relations and Political Science

Geneva, Switzerland

Sep 2019 - 2024 (expected)

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES (IHEID)

- Doctoral Project: 'Authenticity, problem construction, and urgency in political discourses' Supervised by Dr. James Hollway and Dr. Yanina Welp
- · Core Courses: Doctoral Seminar; Survey Experiments; Social Networks; Statistics; Identity and Violence

Masters in International Relations and Political Science

Geneva, Switzerland

Sep 2017 - Aug 2019

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES (IHEID)

 Masters' Thesis: 'The Construction of a Migrant Crisis - The Venezuelan Migration to Brazil' Supervised by Dr. Melanie Kolbe and Dr. Graziella Moraes Silva

Bachelor of Arts in Political Science and Sociology (Double Degree)

Birmingham, United States

• Recipient of 4 years of scholarship as a Student-Athlete for Soccer in a NCAA Division 1 University

Research Experience ____

UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA AT BIRMINGHAM

Research Assistant Geneva. Switzerland

CENTER FOR INTERNATIONAL ENVIRONMENTAL STUDIES (CIES)

Sep 2020 - Present

Jan 2013 - Jun 2017

- Assist with the theoretical, methodological, and empirical developments in data and analysis for across various domains of global governance in the 'PANARCHIC: Power and Networks and the Rate of Change in Institutional Complexes' project funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF)
- Help with the development data infrastructure and statistical methods in R, offered as an emsemble of R packages, for the gathering, consolidating, and analyzing global governance data
- Train and manage research assistants to work with data colletion, R package development, GitHub branching, website design, and among other programmatic issues related to the project

Publications and Working Papers

Which Amazon Problem? Problem-constructions and Transnationalism in Brazilian Presidential Discourse since 1985 (with Livio Silva-Muller)

Environmental Politics

DOI: 10.1080/09644016.2023.2220639

June 2023

Radiating Truthiness: Authenticity performances in politics in Brazil and the United States

REVISE AND RESUBMIT IN POLITICAL STUDIES

Managing imprecise dates in R with messydates (with James Hollway)

WORKING PAPER

It is urgent that we look at urgency in politics: An introduction to urgency analysis

WORKING PAPER

Teaching

Fundamentals of R (co-lecturered with Livio Silva-Muller)

Fall 2022, Spring 2023, Fall 2023

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES (IHEID)

- Provides a hands-on introduction to data science using the R programming language and software
- Teaches students how to import, transform, analyze, and visualize various types of data in R
- Demonstrates practical applications of R for the analysis of environment, finance, and conflict data

Intermediate R for Social Science Research

Fall 2023

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES (IHEID)

- Provides an applied introduction to various research methods using R
- Teaches students how to select and carry-on different types of statistical modeling; how to work with unsupervised approaches for text analysis; and how to analyze, visualize, and model survey data

Conference Presentations

Anti-PC and Authenticity: Authenticity performances in politics in Brazil and the United States

Los Angeles, United States

AMERICAN SOCIOLOGICAL ASSOCIATION

August 2022

• Regular session on the 'Party and its base: Understanding the relationship between political professionals and their audiences'

Amazonian Repertoires in Brazilian Presidential Discourse since 1985

Online

LATIN AMERICAN STUDIES ASSOCIATION

May 2022

• Panel on the 'Forest Managements Conservation and Agricultural Production'

Performing Authenticity: Anti-Politically Correct Discourses in Brazil and the United States

Online

SWISS POLITICAL SCIENCE ASSOCIATION

February 2022

• Workshop session on 'Liberal Ideology and Cultural Backlash'

The Construction of a Migratory Crisis: The Venezuelan Migration to Brazil

Online

LATIN AMERICAN STUDIES ASSOCIATION

May 2020

• Panel on 'Las distintas violencias de las migraciones'

Invited talks

How has the Brazilian Amazon been Constructed as a Problem? Presidential Speeches and Transnational Politics since 1985

Geneva, Switzerland

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES (IHEID)

October 2022

• Invited talk at the Center for International Environmental Studies (CIES) Seminar

Anti-Political Correctness and Authenticity: Authenticity performances in politics in Brazil and the United States

Lausanne, Switzerland

Université de Lausanne

March 2022

• Invited talk for the Research Group on Elections and Political Citizenship (GREC)

Packages_

manydata Contributor

AN R PORTAL FOR GLOBAL GOVERNANCE DATA

messydates Contributor

AN R PACKAGE FOR EXTENDED DATE/TIME FORMAT (EDTF)

manynet Contributor

An R package to make, manipulate, and map myriad networks

migraph Contributor

AN R PACKAGE WITH TOOLS FOR MULTIMODAL AND MULTILEVEL NETWORK ANALYSIS

manypkgs Contributor

AN R PACKAGE TO SUPPORT THE CREATION OF NEW MANY PACKAGES

manyenviron Contributor

AN R DATA PACKAGE ON ENVIRONMENTAL AGREEMENTS

manystates Contributor

AN R DATA PACKAGE ON SOVEREIGN STATES

poldis Author

AN R PACKAGE WITH TOOLS FOR ANALYZING POLITICAL DISCOURSES OVER TIME

Awards and Honors

- UAB Presidential Honors List 2013, 2015, 2016 and 2017
- Conference USA Academic Honor Medal (2015)
- National Soccer Coaches Association of America NCAA Scholar All-South Region Team (2016)
- Conference USA Commissioner's Honor Roll (2013 2016)
- Conference USA All-Academic Team (2016)
- College Sports Information Directors of America Academic All-District Team (2016)

Skills

- Languages: Portuguese (native); English (fluent); French (proficient); Italian (intermediate); Spanish (basic)
- Programming languages: R (proficient); Python (intermediate); C (basic); Bash (basic); Java (basic)
- Markup languages: Markdown (proficient); LaTeX (advanced); HTML (advanced); CSS (intermediate)

References

James Hollway

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR OF INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS AND POLITICAL SCIENCE

THE GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF INTERNATIONAL AND DEVELOPMENT STUDIES (IHEID)

• Email: james.hollway@graduateinstitute.ch

Yanina Welp

RESEARCH FELLOW

ALBERT HIRSCHMAN CENTRE ON DEMOCRACY (AHCD)

• Email: yanina.welp@graduateinstitute.ch

Additional references available upon request